原视频名：SpaceX's Starship SN10 Successfully Lands After Amazing Flight.
Dismantles Itself Spectacularly.
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/CF9mdMI1qxM
原视频发布日期：20210304
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Today SpaceX down in Boca Chica had another test flight of a Starship prototype.
今天SpaceX在Boca Chica又进行了一次Starship原型机的试飞
Starship SN10 took to the skies on its second attempt.
Starship SN10进行了第二次试飞
the first attempt counted all the way down and aborted at T-0.1 seconds
第一次试飞在倒计时0.1秒时就中止了
but later in the day all the engines took to flight.
但在当天晚些时候 所有的发动机都起飞了
Now apparently the earlier abort was because one engine was producing too much power.
那么显然之前的中止是因为一台发动机产生了过大的推力
And so they had decided to just reset the automatic systems and allow it to do what it wanted.
所以他们决定重设自动系统 让它做它想做的事
I don't know if that's relevant but later on in the flight when they were down to two engines,
我不知道这是否相关 但在后来的飞行过程中 在只剩下两台发动机运行的时候
it was very obvious that one engine was burning a slightly different color than another one.
很明显 一台发动机与另一台发动机燃烧的颜色略有不同
this would typically indicate that you're perhaps running fuel rich.
这通常表明发动机在富燃运行
Therefore you're more orange because there's more carbon in the exhaust that's able to emit black body radiation.
因此火焰的颜色更偏橙色 因为废气里有更多的碳 能够发出黑体辐射
Other than that everything went as it has before.
除此之外 一切都和以前一样
right down to the vehicle getting as high as it would at a T+4:20 before turning off its engines.
直到T+4:20 航天器在关闭发动机前 达到最高点
From here it transitions into the horizontal skydive orientation.
从这里开始 它过渡到水平跳伞式下落 的方向
You get a great view of that square area of thermal protection tiles are being tested.
这下你可以好好地看到那个用来测试的排成方形区域的隔热瓦
Obviously they're not needed at these velocities.
很明显 在这样的速度下不需要它们
but they do want to make sure they stay attached
但工作人员想确保隔热瓦能好好地固定上
because it would suck to lose them at orbital speeds.
因为在轨道速度下 失去隔热瓦会很糟
And again they demonstrated that the vehicle could maintain control in the horizontal orientation.
他们再次验证了航天器可以在水平方向上保持控制
But what they really wanted to do was demonstrate that it would be able to land.
但他们真正想做的是验证它的着陆能力
The previous two have failed for various reasons.
前两次在各种原因的影响下都失败了
This time the plan was to light up three engines in quick succession.
这次的计划是连续点燃三台发动机
And then shut them down relieving only one.
然后关闭它们 只让一台发动机继续运行
So you'll see that all three lit and then two shut down very quickly leaving one to perform the landing.
所以你会看到 三台发动机都点燃了 然后两台很快就关闭了 只留下一台发动机进行着陆
Now we'll talk about that fire later.
那么我们后面再谈着火这个问题
Great thing is it did actually slow down and put itself on the pad although not as gently as it would like.
好事是它确实放慢了速度 并成功着陆 虽然并不是那么轻柔的着陆
If you looked very carefully there you might have seen a bit of a bounce.
如果你仔细看 会发现有一点反弹
But this was a massive success.
但这是一个巨大的成功
The first real demonstration of Starship's landing maneuver.
这是Starship着陆动作的第一次真正验证
There were a lot of doubts about whether this would be controllable.
当时有很多人怀疑这个过程是否可以控制
Whether they could put it on target.
他们是否能把它放在目标上
and yeah we saw it on the third attempt albeit not perfect.
是的 我们在这第三次尝试时就看到了 尽管并不完美
There's a bit of fire going on there.
底部有一点着火
Something possibly got damaged.
有东西可能被损坏了
And I'm sure the people were starting to celebrate.
而我敢肯定 人们已经开始庆祝了
And of course the SpaceX webcast finished before we got to see what happens next.
当然 SpaceX的网络直播在我们发现接下来的事情之前就结束了
But of course SpaceX weren't the only people pointing cameras at this.
但当然 除了SpaceX 也有其他人把镜头对准这里
There were rocket watchers who had come from all over the country.
还有从全国各地赶来的火箭观察者
And Everyday Astronaut was in the process of
而每日宇航员此时正在
winding up his broadcast thanking everybody out there when this happened.
结束直播 感谢观众 与此同时这件事就这么发生了
Oh man I can't believe that. We need to start dumping footage don't we.
哦 兄啊 我不能相信 我们需要开始导出视频了 不是吗
We need to start dumping footage.
我们需要开始导出视频
Oh. Oh god it just blew up.
哦 上帝 它就炸了
It just blew up.
它就炸了
缠绕复合材料压力容器(Composite Overwrapped Pressure Vessel)飞走了
What.
什
What just happened.
发生甚么事了
[Laughter]
[笑声]
So yeah what did just happen.
所以是的 刚才发生了什么
Well obviously it exploded.
很明显 它爆炸了
Do we have any clues as to what might have gone wrong.
我们能发现它出问题的任何线索吗
So let's look at some other footage.
那么让我们看看其他视频吧
This is LabPadre's live stream and they have a really stable camera.
这是LabPadre的直播 他们的相机非常稳定
Again you see the vehicle coming down.
同样的 你可以看到航天器再次着陆
You can see the landing legs deploying there.
你可以看到着陆腿在那里展开
Little bit of activity.
那有一点儿动静
A lot of fire coming out of the side there and a bounce you can really see the bounce here.
很多火焰从侧面射出 还有一点弹跳
It's also a 4K stream so we can get a close look at those legs deploying
这也是一个4K的直播 所以我们可以近距离看到这些着陆腿的部署过程
or are not actually deploying.
或者实际上没有部署成功
So it looked like three of the legs deployed and locked in place.
那么看起来有三条腿已经展开并锁住了
Well three of them just kind of swung back and forth
好吧 另外三个只是在来回摆动
and well we're not in a position to do the job for which they were intended.
而且没法完成它们的工作
Now these legs are a temporary solution.
那么 这些腿只是一个临时解决方案
They are designed to get crushed by the force of the impact absorbing the energy.
这是一种类似粉碎芯的结构 可以被冲击的力量压碎 并吸收能量
And of course having only three of them instead of six means there's a lot less crush to go around.
当然 只有三条腿而不是六条腿意味着压碎的部分少了很多
And that probably contributed to having a lot more force applied to the body.
而这可能也导致更多的力量施加到了箭体上
When the smoke cleared this was very much the leaning tower of Starship.
当烟雾散去后 这就很像是Starship斜塔
It had collapsed onto the rear without any of the legs being visible.
Starship一屁股坐在地上 看不到任何的腿
There was no space between the skirt and the ground.
裙板和地面之间没有任何空间
Using the same video stream I also plotted like little vertical slices and put them side by side.
使用相同的视频流 我还把每一帧图像做成垂直切片并拼接起来
Basically the idea is to try and figure out the velocity that this thing was going.
基本上 我是想试图搞清楚航天器的速度
And one of the things that was very obvious was that it wasn't really decelerating at this point.
其中一件事是非常明显的 就是它这时并没有真正减速
It was moving downwards at a constant 15 miles per hour or thereabouts.
它以6.7m/s左右的速度 匀速向下运动
And that seems excessive.
这似乎有点过高了
But I think I'm more interested in the fact that it didn't seem to be slowing down at all.
但我更感兴趣的是它在这段运动中似乎根本没有减速的事实
During the landing process if you remember they wanted to light all three engines.
在着陆过程中 如果你还记得他们想把三台发动机都点燃
Because it previously had problem with a single engine not lighting when they tried to fly with two.
是因为之前他们尝试用两台发动机飞行时 出现了一台发动机无法点火的问题
And the plan was to relight three and then pick the best two and then shut them down progressively.
而计划是将三台发动机重新点燃 然后挑选出最好的两台发动机 然后逐步关闭它们
And finally leave a single engine to do the landing.
最后留下一个发动机进行着陆
So this is the official SpaceX footage
那么这是以四分之一的速度播放的SpaceX官方的视频
basically showing the flip and burn maneuver playing at one quarter speed.
基本上是展示了翻转和点火的机动
It looks unearthly.
它看起来不可思议
It looks unreal.
它看起来不真实
But yeah you can see all three engines firing there.
但是 是的 你可以看到所有的三台发动机在那里点火
And now one gets shut down and the second one shuts down almost instantly.
而现在一台关闭 而第二台几乎也是立刻关闭
There was some question about that.
关于这件事 有一些问题
Furthermore the second shutdown seems to blow out a lot of methane.
第二台发动机关闭时 似乎吹出了大量的甲烷
And we get a fair amount of combustion going on
而且有相当一部分甲烷在继续燃烧
as it's transitioning into the final hover and controlled landing with that single engine.
此时航天器正使用单台发动机过渡到最后的悬停和可控的着陆时
That single engine should have enough thrust to be able to stop this thing.
单台发动机应该有足够的推力来让航天器停下来
From this angle you also see that it had to do a fairly large translation back towards the pad.
从这个角度你还可以看到它必须做一个相当大的平移来回到着陆场
It had overshot by lighting three engines.
点燃三台发动机进行翻转的过程 导致了这个平移
And yeah that's that engine that shut down.
是的 就是那台关闭了的发动机
It seems there's a lot more methane venting during this final part of the process.
看来在这最后的过程中 还有很多甲烷在排放
I think there may be a stuck valve at this point
我想这时可能有一个阀门卡住了
because of course after the heavy landing
当然是因为在较重的着陆之后
there was enough stuff burning on the ground
地上有很多东西在燃烧
that they needed to employ the water deluge system to help control the situation.
于是他们需要使用喷水系统来帮忙控制局面
So that fire was coming from one of the ground service pipes.
那么 那窜火是从一个地面服务管道里出来的
I think this is how they would normally load methane into the rocket.
我想这就是正常情况下甲烷加注的管道
You can see that it's shooting down initially and generating that cryogenic white cloud of very cold gas.
你可以看到它一开始是向下排出气体 并产生低温白色气体
And over time that the flame burns down into it
而过了一会之后 火焰向下燃烧
but it's not coming from one of the engines.
但这并不是来自其中一台发动机(的火焰)
That's the important thing.
这很重要
This is not an engine problem in this case.
在这种情况下 这不是发动机的问题
This is definitely a plumbing problem, a problem with the vehicle fuel system.
这绝对是一个管道的问题  一个与航天器燃料系统相关的问题
And again you see that bounce which cannot be healthy for something that size.
同时 一样地 可以看到那种反弹 这对于这么大的航天器来说是不好的
LabPadre also has some of the best footage of the development of the explosion.
LabPadre也有爆炸发生时画面最好的视频
So watch at the bottom fins right.
那么请看底部的翼面
First of all you'll see a puff of smoke coming out of the vents that are related to the engines.
首先 你会看到一股烟从发动机的排气口喷出
See that black puff and then the oxygen tank essentially splits into and the vehicle goes upwards.
看到那团黑烟了吗 然后液氧储罐基本上就裂开了 航天器就往上飞
What's happening is that tank splits all the gas pressures pushing the vehicle up.
这里发生的事情是 液氧储罐裂开时产生的所有气体压力 推动航天器上升
But once that has gone up there's more pressure in the tank above it.
但一旦航天器上升 其上的储罐里就会有更大的压力
And that actually pushes out the bulkhead although we can't see it on this footage.
而这实际上是把隔板推出去了 虽然我们在这段录像中看不到它的存在
I want you to appreciate there's enough pressure in those tanks that when the tank fails.
我想让你知道的是 在储罐出现故障的时候 其中有着足够的压力
That is entirely responsible for pushing the vehicle upwards and causing its destruction.
储罐中的压力是让航天器上升 并使之摧毁的原因
The fire is sort of an incidental effect in this case.
在这种情况下 火是一种附带的效果
It may make the launch a little more aggressive
它可能会使这种发射 更有侵略性
but a tank failure like that would send the vehicle upwards and be quite spectacular on its own.
但这样的储罐故障 会让航天器往上飞 本身就很壮观
It's actually similar to some earlier Starship test article failures where it was just a pressure test failure.
这其实类似于早期的一些Starship压力测试的失败
So this is like the last frame before we see the things starting to move.
那么这差不多是一切开始运动前的最后一帧
Look at the nose cone.
看看鼻锥
Look how that is crumpling in.
看它是如何扭曲的
Remember there's a big mass of liquid oxygen in that nose in the very tip.
要知道 在航天器的最顶端有一大团液氧
And the rest of the vehicle is getting pushed up against this
而航天器的其他部分被推到了这个位置上
which is causing everything to crinkle as it leaves the ground.
导致所有的东西在离开地面的时候都皱了起来
Now NASASpaceflight they have a different angle it's sort of at 90 degrees.
那么NASASpaceflight他们有一个不同的角度 差不多和之前的角度差了90度
Watch on the left side at the bottom.
看看左边的底部
You see how this is an asymmetric blast.
你会发现这是一个不对称的爆炸
And because it starts on one side that causes the whole upper part to flip over.
因为它是从一边开始的 所以整个上部都会翻转过来
So it actually does the whole belly flop maneuver albeit a slightly lower altitude.
所以它实际上做了整个机腹俯冲向下的机动 尽管高度稍低
In this one you can see the landing and the whole thing just flattens out instantly.
在这段视频里 你可以看到在着陆的时候 整个航天器都瞬间变平了
That shows me that by the time it landed the bulkhead between the fuel tank and the oxygen tank had failed.
这说明在它着陆的时候 燃料储罐和液氧储罐之间的隔板已经失效了
Otherwise there would be some sort of gas pressure in there and the thing would have gone sideways.
否则里面会有某种程度的气体压力 因此航天器则会侧翻
The good news for SpaceX engineers as you can see from this angle
对于SpaceX工程师来说 好消息是 从这个角度可以看到
that the tiles are still attached even after that heavy landing.
即使在重重的着陆之后 隔热瓦仍旧连接在航天器的外壁上
Again look at the bottom of the rocket watch for the puffs of smoke and then we get this pressure failure.
再看一下火箭的底部 注意看烟雾喷出的情况 然后我们就会看到这个失压的情况
You can see the tank coming apart.
你可以看到储罐正在解体
There you can't see any visible combustion.
你看不到有任何可见的燃烧
So I think it's the pressure that's driving this.
所以我认为是压力导致了这种情况
Of course we're mixing liquid oxygen and methane
当然 液氧和甲烷正在混合
so the next frame we see a very involved combustion process.
那么在下一帧里我们看到了一个非常复杂的燃烧过程
But my point is I think this is pressure based
但我的观点是 这是基于压力的(爆炸)
although the fire might have weakened something.
虽然(之前的)火灾可能已经削弱了一些东西
It might have caused some other leak or some damage.
可能造成了一些其他的泄漏或者是损坏
And then of course the whole thing continues into a giant conflagration
然后 当然 整个事情继续 变成了一团巨大的火焰
becomes fodder for clickbaity videos on youtube.
成为油管上标题党视频的素材
We can put these side by side if you just want to compare.
如果你只是想比较一下 我们可以把这些并排放在一起
It's hard to synchronize because the cameras have different frame rates.
这两个视频很难同步 因为相机的帧率不同
But again yeah it is not a pretty sight a lot of debris flying everywhere.
但一样的是 这不是一个漂亮的景象 很多碎片到处飞
So to summarize I don't have a smoking gun
那么总结一下 我没有确凿的证据
but what we do have is the understanding that the landing was faster.
但我们知道的是着陆速度较快
The legs were not properly deployed.
着陆腿的展开有问题
It probably damaged something which ultimately led to a pressure failure in the oxygen tank.
损坏了什么东西 最终导致液氧储罐失压
Very quickly followed by the failure of the bulkhead between the two tanks.
很快 两个储罐之间的隔板也发生了故障
And that of course drove the second flight.
而这当然也推动了第二次飞行
I wanted to joke that this is an example of SpaceX's RUSH development, Rapid Unplanned Second Hop.
我想开玩笑说 这是SpaceX的RUSH开发的一个例子 即意外的第二次迅速跳跃
But the loss of the vehicle minutes after the landing shouldn't overshadow the fact that
但着陆几分钟后航天器的损失 不应该掩盖这样的事实
SpaceX have successfully demonstrated the transition from the belly flop into the landing orientation.
也就是SpaceX已经成功验证了从腹部向下到着陆方向的过渡
This carefully put the vehicle on the pad.
而航天器的着陆力度问题
They obviously need to do a little bit of work in making this more reliable.
则显然需要他们再多做一点工作 使之更可靠
But this is a huge win showing that SpaceX are capable of doing what they said they would do.
但这是一个巨大的胜利 表明SpaceX有能力做到他们所说的事情
I hear that there were people from NASA there
我听说有NASA的人在那里
that were representing the human landing system program.
是代表载人登陆系统项目的
so SpaceX has Starship proposed for that
那么SpaceX为该项目的提案是(月球版)Starship
although this particular maneuver will not be required for the lunar Starship.
虽然这个特殊的机动在月球版Starship上并不需要
Also in the last few days, Yusaku Maezawa as part of his dear moon program
另外 在最近几天 作为亲爱的月球 计划的一部分
invited applications for astronauts that will join him on his flight around the moon.
前泽友作邀请人们提交做宇航员的申请 来加入他的绕月飞行
They said 2023.
他们说2023年就能进行这个计划
I highly suspect that that is Elon time and will be pushed out by quite a bit.
我高度怀疑那是马一龙时间 (实际)会被推后不少
But regardless I'm sure there are a lot of people applying to fly on this thing right now.
但不管怎样 我相信现在肯定有很多人在申请乘坐这个东西
I'm hoping that they will solve all the technical problems before that happens.
我希望他们能在这之前解决所有的技术问题
But yeah great success very spectacular.
不过 是的 伟大的成功还是非常的壮观
Here's hoping that SN11 solves all those problems and can fly again in more controlled fashion.
希望SN11能解决所有这些问题 并能以更可控的方式再次飞行
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]